There can be trades that make you money
that are valid positive expectancy
opportunities, but are still bad trades
to take. And these are trades that most
traders are spending most of their time
taking because most traders never really
think about it properly. They think the
only questions that matter are whether a
trade is valid and whether it can make
them money or not. And fair enough, that
obviously matters, but if you want to be
professional, that's not the only thing
that matters because every time you open
a trade, you're making a resource
allocation decision. And if you don't
think about that properly, you could
make money from your trading and still
trade like an amateur, which means
amateurish performance, and no one wants
that. So, in this video, I want to
explain how I think about opportunity
costs in trading, why is some valid
opportunities are still bad decisions,
what I learned about all of this from
strippers. Yes, I said strippers there.
And a simple exercise that you can start
using to review your trades so you stop
wasting time on the wrong opportunities.
Now, for most people, when you think
about opportunity cost, you usually
think about money that you'll
potentially miss out on. And obviously,
that matters, but in trading, it's more
than just that because when you open a
trade, you're not just risking capital.
There are also other costs involved as
well. And if you ignore them, you can
end up making decisions that look fine
on face value, but are actually pretty
when you step back and look at the
bigger picture. The first one is time.
Most traders never ask themselves a
really basic question, which is am I
actually being paid well enough for
this? You see, in a normal job, you
exchange your time for money or
expertise for money, depending on the
job. In trading, you do the same. Except
as well as exchanging your time for
money, you're also risking your own
capital. So, if your trades give you a
bad return relative to the amount of
time they take, that really does matter
because the time spent sitting with a
position could have gone into a better
opportunity or into something else
entirely. Like if you could earn the
same or more money per hour in a regular
job without also having to risk your own
money, then from an opportunity cost
point of view, your trading obviously
isn't making much sense. Then obviously
you've got capital. If your money's tied
up in one position, it can't be used
elsewhere. So by being in that trade,
you're making the implicit statement
that this is the best use of this
capital right now. Now obviously I'm not
saying that you need to have psychic
powers and must somehow know every other
possible opportunity out there at any
moment. That would be ridiculous. But
I'm saying that based on your market
selection process and the context that
you've analyzed across the markets that
you're following, you should be able to
judge what sort of opportunities you're
likely to find and whether that's a good
enough use of your capital relative to
other markets. So even before you click
buy or sell on a trade, you've already
made a resource allocation decision by
choosing where to focus. And then that
brings us on to mental energy, which
people massively underestimate. When
you've got a trade open, it takes up a
lot of your attention and energy, your
focus. Even if there are no active
decisions or actions that you need to
take, it's still living rent-free in
your head. And that's why people
struggle to focus on their work when
they've got a trade open or
conversations or anything else. When
they've got a position open, it occupies
their minds. But it also goes beyond
that. You see, analysis, forecasting,
planning, decision making, all of these
things take up a lot of cognitive
energy. So if you burn that energy on a
sub-standard opportunity just cuz you
want to be in a trade, and then
something better comes up later in your
session, you're going to be approaching
the better opportunity, the one that
deserves more of your effort, with less
capability than what you had earlier.
I've seen so many times over the years
that one of the reasons traders make so
many mistakes or miss important signs in
the markets right in front of their eyes
is because they've wasted too much
mental energy earlier in the session
scanning endless markets, trading
scrappy opportunities, basically burning
themselves out. So, it's not just a
question of whether an opportunity is
valid, it's whether it justifies the
opportunity cost. And by the way, if
you're already realizing that you don't
really have a proper framework for
assessing any of this and that you've
mostly just been following a strategy
and trying to find setups, I've put
together a whole training series that
will help you. It will show you how to
analyze context, how to assess
opportunities the right way, and build
the actual skills behind doing all of
this rather than just following someone
else's strategy and hoping it turns out
all right. So, the link is down below.
It's free to sign up. Go and check it
out. So, what's the right way to think
about your trade opportunities?
Well, I had one of the best lessons ever
about this and it came from one of the
most unlikely places.
So, years ago we had an office on Fleet
Street in London, but at the time I was
living outside of London and I kept
having the same problem a few times a
week. I'd basically work late, miss the
last train by accident cuz I didn't
notice the time, and then be left with
the option of either getting a black cab
all the way home. This is before Uber
was really a thing in London, so it was
going to be like over 100 pounds to get
back, or booking a hotel room. So, in my
mid-20s wisdom, I came up with an
alternative that I thought was this
clever master plan. I'd just go
somewhere else that was still open at
that time, have some drinks, then either
get the first train back in the morning
or go straight back to the office and
keep working. Back then, my philosophy
was basically I'll sleep when I'm dead.
Now, it's more like pipe and slippers by
9:00 p.m.
But, being the wild degenerate that I
was back then with more money than
sense,
I decided that the place I'd go to each
night was a strip club in Leicester
Square. Now, I'd like to tell you that
that was just the only place that was
open at the time, but let's be honest
here. I just hope my mom's not watching.
Sorry, Mom. Honestly though, and
whenever I tell people this, they never
believe me, but truthfully, I was not
going there for lap dances or anything
like that. I was going to literally sit
at the bar and have a chat.
Or as my friend Christian used to say to
me, you go there to meet your future
ex-girlfriends, which actually wasn't
too far off. I got to know some of them
pretty well. One of them had a masters
in literature, we'd talk about books.
One of them was a psychologist, it was
hilarious. It was like a networking
event in lingerie, them obviously, not
me. One night, two of the girls
explained something to me that I've
never forgotten, because I thought it
was such a great lesson for so many
things in life, not just for strip
clubs, and it was the concept of
strip-onomics. So, they explained to me
that there was a huge range in terms of
how much money different punters would
spend across the night. So, some people
would spend next to nothing other than
buying drinks, like me. Some might get a
cheap lap dance, others would drop
serious money in the VIP booths. So, a
girl could spend a whole night talking
to a bloke who was never going to spend
much, and therefore waste all of her
time and come away with eff all to show
for it. But, the newer girls in the club
didn't really know how to judge that.
So, they just treated everyone equally
like they were an opportunity. But, the
experienced girls didn't. They learned
to spot the cues, how someone was
dressed, what they ordered, how they
behaved, what watch they had on, what
they said in the first interactions, and
if the signs weren't right, they were
ruthless. They'd cut their losses and
move on and not go back. You'd literally
see some guys sitting there wondering
why no one was talking to them the whole
night. Now, of course, sometimes they
got it wrong. Sometimes the bloke who
looked like he was skint or said the
wrong thing would end up spending a
fortune, and the one who ticked all the
boxes was all show and no wallet. But,
over time, the girls who allocated their
time better made much more money, and
that's the difference between finishing
the night with a few hundred quid or
having enough money to pay for a month's
rent in Chelsea, which happens to be
where a lot of them lived. And that
principle is exactly the same in
trading, just less fake eyelashes and
obviously more clothes, less lingerie.
But, hopefully, telling you that story
will help it stick in your minds like it
has for me. All these years later, I
still remember it. So, most traders
behave like the new girls. They see
anything vaguely valid, anything that
resembles an opportunity, and they cling
onto it. Otherwise, they might miss out
on it. But professionals don't think
like that. They also understand that not
all positive expectancy situations are
equal opportunities for them. Some
deserve priority, some are decent, not
great, some are technically tradeable
but still a poor use of resources. And
that's a key point, because something
being tradeable is not the same as
something worth taking. And so, that's
why with my trades, I think about
opportunities being across two simple
scales. The first is expectancy, from
lower to higher. And obviously here,
we're only talking about positive
expectancy, because if expectancy is
negative or base rate, it isn't an
opportunity in the first place.
And the second is the likely holding
period of the trade, or estimated
holding period, what you can anticipate
from what you can detect from the
current and potential future context.
So, in other words, how long I'd expect
the trade to be open in order to realize
the full opportunity.
And once you think in this way, you can
imagine four broad categories. The best
category is high expectancy with a low
holding period. Those trades are like
gold dust. So, for me, this might be a
free-flowing market where there's
potential for a high momentum breakout
or reversal, either price is going to
overcome a big shift in activity, or
that shift activity is going to cause
the move to collapse and head strongly
in the other direction. And when it does
go, it's likely to go quickly and open
up the higher-order outcomes. So, you've
got what is potentially a runaway trade.
So, that's a lovely situation to be in.
I see these opportunities as like a huge
bonus on top of my normal returns. They
don't come as frequently, but when they
do, you grab onto them. And actually,
related to that, here's another little
insight for you, cuz it's something I
think traders have backwards in their
mind.
When a trade ends up losing, right? So,
it's hit your stop loss or whatever, it
seems like most traders would rather see
it struggle there for a while. Like it
really sort of battles with the level,
rather than it just heading directly to
their stop loss. It's like they want the
validation that they at least picked up
on something that was going on there.
But, if you've already got evidence in
your ability to identify genuine
positive expectancy opportunities, so
you know if you spot an opportunity, it
was positive expectancy, it was valid,
then it's so much better for the price
to just shoot directly to your stop loss
as quickly as possible if it's going to
be a losing trade. And if traders moan
about those situations when it goes
directly to their stop loss, but I'm
grateful for them. A loss is a loss. Why
do I want to watch a stop loss dance for
a few hours when I can get the outcome
immediately and just move my resources
elsewhere?
So, I understand the mindset there. Then
you've got the high expectancy and high
holding period trades. So, these ones
are still decent opportunities, but just
more resource heavy than the previous
category.
So, for me, an example of this might be
a market where I can see that the higher
order outcomes are still valid, but the
move is maybe more likely to develop
through structure over time rather than
an immediate momentum move. So, I can
still access those higher order outcomes
as part of the opportunity, but it's
just going to take a while to get there.
So, the opportunity is still good. It
just costs more in terms of time, tying
up the capital, and attention.
And then you've got lower expectancy
with a low holding period. So, the
expectancy is in proportion to the
amount of time you're going to be in
that trade for. And I really like these
ones because there's not much decision
making once they're open. They're quick.
They're mainly about first order
outcomes, so no trade management
decisions, just in and out. So, a good
example here for me is like range
trading or something like that, where
you might get several opportunities
across a relatively short period of time
with the same broader piece of analysis
because the opportunities just keep
coming. You know, you're in, out, in,
out.
Strike your order out. For sake. So,
those ones might not be the spectacular
runaway trades, but it can still be a
good use for your resources because they
don't take too long. I think these like
my bread and butter trades. They're
straightforward, they give you a decent
baseline return over time, and then the
sexier trades build on top of that like
a bonus. So, you've got your steady
returns, then you've got the bonuses
every now and then. And then there's the
category that we should all avoid like
the plague.
Lower expectancy with a high holding
period. These ones are an absolute piss
take. They tie up your money, they live
rent-free in your head for a long time,
and the return is low for the amount of
time and energy that they take. So, for
me that would mean slow moving markets,
flat structure, low conviction trends,
or markets like Euro pound where you can
actually feel yourself aging while you
wait for something to actually happen
that's meaningful.
But the problem is most traders spend
most of their time in this category.
They don't realize it, but they do
because there are more of these types of
opportunities than any of the others.
Maybe the amount of opportunities that
fit in this category are about the same
as all the others put together. So, they
spend their time in mediocre, slow,
draggy sort of situations that don't
justify the resources that are being
consumed by it. And then there are all
the knock-on effects of that because
people get bored, they get frustrated,
they become too aggressive with their
trade management because they want it to
be something that it's not, or they
become too reactive to everything that
happens and exit early because they
think about how long they've been
holding on for and then they want to
take what they've got. Or they start
forcing something to happen because
they're sick of waiting. So, it's not
just that the trade has a heavy
opportunity cost, but it also drags
their behavior down with it. So, it's a
lose-lose situation in some ways. Now,
just to be clear, these examples that
I've walked through are just to help you
understand the principles better. There
are obviously many other types of
opportunities, you can categorize things
how you want, and things fall on a scale
rather than into four tidy boxes like
this. So, I don't want you doing what
everyone seems to love doing in this
industry, and turning this into some
sort of laminated cheat sheet that you
can try and follow for everything, and
identify all of this as a range trade,
it goes here, this this. The point is
the thought process. The point is the
principle I'm talking about, the way of
thinking. And here's the thing, this way
of thinking doesn't just affect whether
I take a trade or not, it also affects
the markets that I even spend time
focusing on, like the ones that I pick
out to put on my short list. It shapes
my market selection process. And this is
one of the biggest changes that I see
happening with traders as they get more
experienced, like it's inevitable, it
happens with everyone.
At the start, you feel scarcity. Every
opportunity feels just as important as
each other. You don't want to miss out
on anything. You jump into every trade,
every setup that you can find. You
follow as many markets as you can.
But then later, after you've taken a lot
of trades, and you've reviewed enough of
your performance, like at the end of the
year, you look at all the trades you
took, you start to realize something,
that actually a minority of your trades,
the smaller portion of them, usually
account for a disproportionate amount of
your results. So, the rest of them took
up your time, energy, attention, but
didn't really contribute as much. It's
basically the Pareto principle.
And once you see that clearly, you stop
treating all opportunities as being
equal, because you do see some of them
as being a waste. So, you start asking
better questions. Like, what sort of
trades are actually more optimal for me?
How do I design my trading process to
find those sorts of opportunities more
often? Which are the trades that tied up
my capital and attention for ages
without really justifying it? What sort
of context gave me the most bang for my
buck? And that is exactly why it is so
important to learn to trade the right
way. Because if you know how to analyze
context properly, and assess
opportunities the right way, rather than
just having a predefined strategy that
you follow each and every time, and try
and spot setups, you can get so much
more out of the markets, and genuinely
be on a path to succeed at this. So, if
you're not already doing that, check out
the training series that's linked down
below, so you can start getting on
track. So, now let's make all of this
practical. I've got a simple exercise
that you can use to start investigating
all of this in your own trading. So,
here's what you want to do.
Open a spreadsheet, and add all of your
profitable trades. Okay, so we're going
to exclude losing trades or break even
trades for now. Some of you sitting
there going, "Okay, I'm going to add two
trades to the spreadsheet then." Okay,
so once your profitable trades sheet,
the next thing you want to do is
normalize all of the returns, so that
they all reflect the same percentage at
risk, and that should be 1%. So, for
example, if you risk 0.5% on a trade,
and made a return of 2%, then you're
going to normalize it, so it would have
been 1% at risk, which means the return
now becomes 4%. So, if you risk 2% on a
trade, and made a 3% return, then if it
was 1% at risk, your return now becomes
1.5%. So, everything is normalized as if
it's the same percentage at risk. Then,
you're going to add the holding time for
each trade. So, you can usually get the
trade entry and exit times from your
broker history, if you're not already
tracking them yourself. So, you can
calculate the total holding time from
that. For most people, it's going to
make the most sense to use hours as the
unit of measurement, but if you're
trading like really, really short-term,
or really long-term, you might want to
change that unit of measurement. You can
make that decision, but hours is usually
good enough. Then, what you do next,
quite simply, is divide the normalized
return by the holding time, and this
will give you a return per hour for each
of the trades. Obviously, it's not
perfect. I'm not saying this is the end
of it, like, "Okay, that gives you your
answer, off you go." But, it gives you
something to start investigating. So,
from there, you can start categorizing
the trades based on whatever factors are
relevant to the way that you're trading.
So, if you're using the Dwymer method,
if you're learning with us, you might
categorize them by the general
opportunity types, like some of the
examples that I gave earlier, or by the
different ways that we assess context,
the different contextual factors. If
you're using some other trading
approach, maybe you'll do it by setup
type, market type, session, time of day,
that's an important one. There are lots
of things that you can investigate that
affect your opportunities in a
consistent way. But, the point is that
now you can start filtering the data and
start looking for patterns. So, what
common features show up in the trades
that offered the best return relative to
the amount of time? What common features
show up in the ones that looked fine in
the moment, but in hindsight were an
inefficient use of resources? That gives
you actual information to start
optimizing from, rather than just
assumptions like most people do. Now,
there are a few caveats here, and
they're really important, so I want you
to pay attention to them.
Firstly, just like I kind of joked about
moments ago, you obviously need a big
enough sample size for any of this to
mean anything. So, if you've got only
got a couple of dozen profitable trades,
or two profitable trades like I joked
about, don't start going through this
and making conclusions, because it's
going to be based on noise. You need a
big enough sample size, and if you don't
know what that sort of sample size is,
or how to collect that, then I'll put a
video up here that we released a little
while ago that talks all about sample
sizes in trading. Secondly, the reason
that we're only including profitable
trades is because losing trades will
massively distort the data. Now,
normally we don't want to just look at
profitable trades for things, because
profitable trades and losing trades are
just two sides of the same coin if it's
a positive expectancy situation.
But, when we're specifically looking at
the holding period, then for example, if
you've got a trade that when it hits the
stop loss it happens within a couple of
hours, but when it's a profitable trade
you're holding onto it for weeks, and
half the time it's a losing trade or
something, then obviously the average
holding period is going to be much lower
than it actually is for the profitable
trades, and it's going to change the way
that you look at the situation. So, if
we want to make the right decisions
about holding period, we need to be just
looking at the profitable trades for
now. And thirdly, and I've said this one
before, but it's important so I'll say
it again. This is just a starting point.
It's not meant to be the be-all,
end-all. You can't just look at the list
and say, "Right, the ones with the
biggest returns per hour are the best
trades." Because that's not necessarily
true. You know, if a trade made you a
10% return, but you held it for 2 weeks,
that still might have been a great use
for your resources because you didn't
need to go and find 10 other
opportunities during that time to
achieve the same result. And a 10%
return is great. So, don't be simplistic
about it. Just use it as a starting
point. And remember, this process mainly
focuses on the time aspect of things.
What you also need to consider is
expectancy, which is something you
should be estimating and tracking
whenever you open a trade. So, this
exercise is not the full answer. It's
just a useful way to start seeing where
your resources are maybe being spent
well, maybe where they're being wasted,
and you can investigate further. Because
over your career, if you do this
properly and regularly, you'll get
better and better at focusing on the
opportunities that genuinely give you
the most bang for your buck, and you'll
stop wasting your life catching minnows
or picking up pennies in front of a
steamroller. You know, when I was 23 and
became a full-time trader for the first
time, I was taking so many trades. I
would barely sleep just so I didn't miss
even the tiniest opportunity in the
Asian session or something like that. I
was glued to the screens all the time,
and I sacrificed a lot in my life
because of that. Then, in the years
after that, I started learning my lesson
and I kept reducing how much I traded to
the point where now I probably open the
fewest trades I ever have because I
figured out over time what's actually
worth my time, effort, and capital. And
it also means that my thinking is much
sharper for the genuinely great
opportunities because I'm not burning
energy on opportunities that aren't that
good at all. And overall, the returns
I'm missing out on by not taking these
smaller opportunities
isn't actually that much. When I weigh
it up against the time spent, the
energy, the sacrifices I made, the
impact on health, relationships, and all
the other things I could have been
doing, it's miles better now. And I hope
that you can make that shift in how you
think about trading without needing to
go through the years of experience and
learning it the hard way like I did.
Amateurs think in terms of scarcity,
professionals think a lot more in terms
of allocation. Not every valid
opportunity deserves your resources. So,
spend the time reviewing your trades,
and if you want the deeper training on
how to analyze context properly, how to
assess opportunities more accurately,
and build the actual skills that will
let you make these decisions the right
way, rather than just guessing your way
through them, then go through that free
training link below. That's exactly what
it's there for. I'll help you understand
the logic behind all of this, why most
traders are still approaching everything
backwards, and what you actually need to
develop if you want to take this
seriously.
Thanks for watching. Hope it was
helpful. And let's just uh keep the
stripper story between us, please. I'm
meant to be trying to find a wife.